<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-08-13T02:46:59+00:00</updated><id>https://mitali-mathur.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Flourishing in the First Year</title><link href="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flourishing in the First Year"/><published>2023-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-blog/"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote this page to share reflections, resources, and routines that helped me feel happy, motivated, and disciplined through the first year of my econ PhD. Coming into a PhD program without a masters degree and after working was definitely an adjustment. As many others have shared before me, you never really know what you’re getting yourself into until you’re here. I tried to prepare myself by speaking to friends currently in PhD programs and by reading blogs. I am a huge proponent of public goods and really appreciate the resources that are online about surviving/thriving the first year. While these were certainly helpful, when I look back on my first year, a resource I wish I had would be a more practical guide. My intention with this page is to provide just that.</p> <p>Many resources emphasize the importance of “studying,” “working in groups” and “learning how to think.” When I got to grad school, everyone said their weekend plans involved “studying” - but I never really knew what that meant. My first quarter was not great academically and there were some things I did well in and some things I did really poorly in, but I learned along the way and improved over the year. I want to emphasize that I do not think there is “one way” or “right way” to do “well” during the first year, but I want to share tips of “a way.” Everyone has their own preferred ways of learning/balancing life and many of my classmates were extremely successful (or more successful!) in navigating first year in their own ways. Therefore, I hope people treat these reflections as an example of some practical tips that worked for me. What worked for me may not work for others and what worked for others may not have worked for me. And that’s ok.</p> <p>Hopefully this page can add some practical context that can help prospective and current first students navigate their own paths!</p> <h1 id="reflections">Reflections</h1> <p>My first year was unlike anything I’ve experienced before in some ways, but very familiar in other ways. The program was more rigorous than the work and schooling I had done before and required a lot of discipline and focus. Despite the rigor, I felt that after a bit of adjusting, I was able to learn what worked for me to be successful and create a sustainable work-life balance.</p> <h2 id="academic-reflections">Academic Reflections</h2> <p>Going back to school for me was hard. I did not have a master’s degree, did not do a pre-doc, and I had worked between my undergraduate schooling and starting graduate school. So I was nervous going into the program. Even during the application process, I felt overwhelmed that I needed a PhD to get into a PhD program and was amazed by some of the profiles of first year students I saw. Everyone told me to take it easy before the program and relax and I say the same thing to prospective students. But I never really followed that advice and I understand that some people might want to do some things before the program.</p> <h3 id="pre-math-camp">Pre-Math Camp</h3> <p>I gave myself a month between my last day at work and the beginning of math camp. I moved in with my parents and spent time with family and friends. I tried to close up some personal projects I was working on. I also tried to get myself set-up for school. I bought an iPad for myself and set-up Notability. I read a few books, skimmed some notes I made in undergrad for my math and econ classes, and watched some random youtube videos. So I wouldn’t say I “studied hard” before math camp at all - rather, I familiarized myself with some core concepts so that I wasn’t lost with the basics. I am actually glad I did and wish I knew how I could have focused my review.</p> <p>Upon reflection, based on my experience, I think the three most important concepts to refresh before math camp that I used throughout the first year are:</p> <ol> <li>Matrix algebra and the definiteness of matrices (to start, I found this series to be a good recap of linear algebra)</li> <li>Proof methods (I reviewed my proofs and analysis class notes to refresh proof by contradiction, contrapositive, induction etc.)</li> <li>Constrained optimization ( I wish I reviewed this more prior to the quarter starting)</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A practical guide to completing the First Year of an Econ PhD program from the organizationally obsessed]]></summary></entry></feed>