<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-08-17T00:19:37+00:00</updated><id>https://mitali-mathur.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Flourishing in the First Year</title><link href="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flourishing in the First Year"/><published>2023-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-blog/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="overview">Overview</h1> <p>I wrote this page to share <i><b>reflections, resources, and routines</b></i> that helped me feel happy, motivated, and disciplined throughout the first year of my econ PhD.</p> <p>Coming into a PhD program without a Masters degree and after working was definitely an adjustment. As many others have shared before me, you never really know what you’re getting yourself into until you’re here. I tried to prepare myself by speaking to friends currently in PhD programs and by reading blogs. I am a huge proponent of public goods and really appreciate the resources that are online about surviving/thriving in the first year. While these were certainly helpful, when I look back on my first year, a resource I wish I had would be a more <i><b>practical guide</b></i>. My intention with this page is to provide just that.</p> <p>Many resources emphasize the importance of “studying,” “working in groups” and “learning how to think.” When I got to grad school, everyone said their weekend plans involved “studying” - but I never really knew what people were doing! While my reflections, routines, and references may seem obvious to me now, I definitely had not developed them or thought about them prior to starting my first year. I thought it might be helpful to document what I wish I knew when I started in this post. I want to emphasize that I do not think there is “one way” or “right way” to do “well” during the first year, but I want to share tips of “a way.” Everyone has their own preferred ways of learning/balancing life and many of my classmates were extremely successful (or more successful!) in navigating first year in their own ways. Therefore, I hope people treat these tips as an <i><b>example</b></i> of some practical techniques that worked for me. What worked for me may not work for others and what worked for others may not have worked for me. And that’s ok.</p> <p>Hopefully this three-part series can add some practical context that can help prospective and current first students navigate their own paths!</p> <h2 id="contents">Contents</h2> <p>View the three parts here:</p> <ul> <li> <a href="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-reflections/">Reflections:</a> This post describes some practical tips I have for finding academic success and feeling socially connected. </li> <li> <a href="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-routines/">Routines:</a> This post shares some examples of routines I found were important to develop and maintain. </li> <li> Resources: This post includes all the study guides I made and organizational tools for streamlining studying. </li> </ul> <h1 id="first-year-video">First Year Video</h1> <p>Here is a quick compilation of some of the fun moments I experienced with the department, my cohort, my friends, and my family. There was indeed a <b>lot</b> of studying every day, but there were also many small outlets of joy that I was lucky enough to find and tried to highlight in this video :)</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <video src="/assets/video/UC%20Davis%20-%20Year%201.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" autoplay="" controls=""/> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My UC Davis Econ PhD Year 1 Experience </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A practical guide to completing the First Year of an Econ PhD program from the organizationally obsessed]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flourishing in the First Year - Part I. Reflections</title><link href="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-reflections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flourishing in the First Year - Part I. Reflections"/><published>2023-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-reflections</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-reflections/"><![CDATA[<p>My first year was unlike anything I’ve experienced before in some ways, but very familiar in other ways. The program was more rigorous than the work and schooling I had done before and required a lot of discipline and focus. Despite the intensity, I felt that after a bit of adjusting, I was able to learn what worked for me to be academically successful and create a sustainable work-life balance.</p> <h1 id="academic-reflections">Academic Reflections</h1> <p>Going back to school for me was hard. I did not have a Masters degree, did not do a pre-doc, and I had worked for 3 years after undergrad and before the start of the Econ PhD. So I was nervous going into the program.</p> <blockquote> <p>The academic twin goals of first year are to build a strong math/econ foundation and to pass preliminary exams.</p> </blockquote> <p>If you’ve completed the first year of an Econ PhD, many of these reflections may seem obvious. But these reflections are what I wish I could go back and tell myself prior to starting. I hope they may help others who are about to start their programs!</p> <h2 id="pre-math-camp">Pre-Math Camp</h2> <p>I gave myself a month between my last day at work and the beginning of math camp. I moved in with my parents and spent time with family and friends. It was nice to relax. I tried to close up some personal projects I was working on. I also tried to get myself set-up for school: I bought an iPad and set-up Notability (which I highly recommend!!). I read a few books, skimmed some notes I made in undergrad for my math and econ classes, and watched some random youtube videos. So I wouldn’t say I “studied hard” before math camp at all - rather, I familiarized myself with some core concepts so that I wasn’t lost with the basics. I am actually glad I did and wish I knew how I could have focused my review better.</p> <p>Based on my experience retrospectively, I think the three most important concepts to refresh before math camp are:</p> <ul> <li> Matrix algebra and the definiteness of matrices </li> <li> Proof methods </li> <li> Constrained optimization </li> </ul> <h2 id="math-camp">Math Camp</h2> <p>Despite math camp being challenging, I am really happy we had it. Firstly, it was a good way to <i><b>get to know my peers</b></i>. We all ate lunch together in the shade outside. I brought a frisbee and threw it around with some folks. I found trying to get to know everyone to be really important - making friends as an adult can be hard!</p> <p>Secondly, I think math camp made me <i><b>internalize the reality that I will definitely be “stuck” on problems</b></i> throughout the PhD, in a more unfamiliar way. In undergrad, when I was stuck, I would think, take a break, and look at textbook examples or past exam questions, which were similar enough that I could figure out how to solve the problem. That was absolutely not the case for some problems during math camp, and subsequent PhD coursework. There are some problems you can’t just “Google” or “ChatGPT” your way to solving. At math camp, I had the opportunity to start thinking about what to do. I went to office hours and compared problem sets with people in my cohort - two tools that I would later use.</p> <p>Lastly, I enjoyed math camp because it gave me an opportunity to try out different routines to find what would work best for me. Since classes started everyday at 9:30am, I figured out my sleep schedule, how long it took me to commute to class, how I should review what we did after class, what worked for meal prep etc. I also had some time to continue setting up my room, do a Costco haul, and get fully ready for the school year.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/3-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/3-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/3-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/4-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/4-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/4-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/4.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Photos from UC Davis's campus </div> <h2 id="classes">Classes</h2> <p>The first day of each class felt great! I felt like I understood what was going on and concepts were familiar. What a false sense of confidence I gave myself… The slow-start was short lived because we immediately began learning at a very quick pace.</p> <p>A few things were different compared to how I learned in undergrad: applications, problem set breadth, predictability, optional work, and the quarter system:</p> <ul> <li> <u><b>Applications:</b></u> There was less of an emphasis in class on solving problems than what I was used to. We had a lot of material to cover and it was completely understandable that professors went through the theory in class and leveraged problem sets and discussion sections to give us opportunities to apply the concepts we learned. For me, this was a bit challenging because I did not directly compare the general notation/definitions to specific applications/examples, so sometimes struggled to understand the purpose of the theory we were learning at the time. </li> <li> <u><b>Problem set breadth:</b></u> There were some elements of problem sets that were extremely challenging. In undergrad, I was used to problems being somewhat adjacent to problems we covered in class. In this program, there were some problems I saw that I had no idea how to even start or attempt since they were so different from the examples in class or textbook problems. This made me realize that understanding core concepts was more important than solving problems – you can’t just learn how to regurgitate a solution to a problem similar to one you’ve seen before, you need to understand the concepts well enough that if you see something completely new, you have the foundations to arrive at a unique solution. </li> <li> <u><b>Predictability:</b></u> In undergrad, I felt that it was a pretty sure bet that we would be tested on specific concepts. There would be one problem on each topic/theme/model covered, so while I studied every topic and tried to ace all parts of a test, I knew that if I was a little stuck on one part, I could still do well overall. The models we learned in the PhD were so complex that in a test, we could only be tested on one or two concepts, but expected to know all - which made it difficult to study for tests. </li> <li> <u><b>Optional work:</b></u> In most of our classes, our grades were solely based on a midterm and final, though some grades incorporated problem sets. There were sometimes optional problem sets that were ungraded. I would always attempt the optional work assigned to us, but sometimes would not spend as much time/effort on them or go out of my way to find additional practice beyond what professors recommended. </li> <li> <u><b>The quarter system:</b></u> The quarter system at UC Davis was such a shock for me. Coming from a school that ran on semesters, I was not used to the lack of breaks within each quarter. For example, there was no time to “catch-up” during Spring break - just a break in between two quarters. </li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>These differences made it difficult for me to be academically successful at the start of my PhD, but over time, I learned how to adjust and felt more engaged and confident as the year progressed.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="studying">Studying</h2> <p>The first test I ever took made me think I would completely fail out. I studied the way I had done in undergrad - I read through notes, re-did some homework problems, skimmed the textbook, and solved a few past exams. But when I saw the exam, questions had unfamiliar twists that I was not able to understand - I bounced around and tried my best, but felt terrible. When the results were posted, I saw myself at the lower end of a whisker, nowhere near the box with the scores from the majority of the class.</p> <p>I then completely pivoted my approach to studying and figured out that for me, an <b>organized and structured approach</b> to studying was most useful. I applied a lot of organizational study tools and techniques to help and saw a massive improvement in my understanding of the course material (which materialized in improved grades and confidence).</p> <p>The main tools I used to study (pretty standard…) were: class notes/lecture notes, problem sets, textbook questions, past exams, papers:</p> <ul> <li> <u><b>Class notes &amp; lecture notes/slides:</b></u> I always took notes separately from lecture slides/lecture notes to capture the explanations professor’s gave in class. I often compared my notes to the lecture slides in case I missed anything. </li> <li> <u><b>Problem sets:</b></u> I found it useful to re-do homeworks and problem set problems, whether optional or not. </li> <li> <u><b>Textbook questions:</b></u> Not all classes had textbooks, but some did. For the classes with associated textbooks, I found it helpful to skim/attempt some additional questions. </li> <li> <u><b> Past exams/prelims:</b></u> If a professor had taught the class before, they often shared past exams (or if they didn’t, sometimes students from older cohorts had them on a Google Drive). I always found it useful to solve these past exams and compare my solutions with the answer keys (if available) or solutions from my peers. </li> <li> <u><b>Papers:</b></u> Sometimes it was helpful to read some of the papers that defined the models for ideas on how the model can be applied or altered in different contexts. </li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>Again, everyone has their own way of studying that works! For me, my previous approach to utilizing these tools in undergrad was not effective because it was not conducive to mastering such a wide breadth of material. Therefore, organizing my studying became extremely important.</p> </blockquote> <p>The main techniques I used to stay organized while studying were having a thematic study plan, making study guides, forming study groups, attending office hours, and employing “what-if” thinking:</p> <ul> <li><u><b>Thematic study plan:</b></u> I realized that for me, studying by themes was most useful. About 2 weeks before each test, I would go through all the resources I had and organize concepts and practice problems by concept/model/theme. Then, I would study everything I could and do all the practice problems I could in a topical manner. This is a different approach to one that goes through problems in chronological order. <ul> <li> For example, let's say I am reviewing past exams chronologically. Suppose the 2022 final has model #1 and model #2. When I move to solving the 2021 final, I might get two different models, model #3 and model #4, since not all models are tested each year. But what if I suddenly see that in the 2019 final, there is a question that is kind of related to model #1? It’s been so long since I reviewed that model and I don't feel confident... I am unsure how to solve the problem when the context is different or the question is asking something else. </li> <li> In contrast, I could study model #1 first - study my notes, do practice problems, and solve past exam questions on model #1. This will help me fully understand the <i><b>core</b></i> of model #1 and allow me to compare/contrast different applications of the model. In this way, I am not memorizing how to solve specific application problems, but really trying to understand all aspects of the model.</li> <li> Example - this was the mapping I used to organize practice problems by themes, which I used during prelim exam preparation. </li> </ul> </li> <li> <u><b>Study guides:</b></u> After we finished learning each topic, I would work on making a study guide to capture the basic, foundational ideas of what we learned. I mainly focused on including simple definitions, formulas, intuition, and problem-solving approaches. I found the act of making them to be very useful in ensuring I understood the basic foundations of each model, was able to compare and contrast different model features, and helpful in creating a plethora of “refresher resources” I could use months later while studying for prelims. <ul> <li> These study guides are foundational in that they do not include deep-dives into every single way each model/topic can be applied. They aren’t pretty or typed into Latex. They’re just basic notes to understand basic concepts. </li> <li> All of my study guides can be found in the resources section! </li> </ul> </li> <li> <u><b>Study groups:</b></u> I utilized studying with my peers when I could and formed a study-group with others who were interested in group studying. Here’s how it worked for us: <ul> <li> About 2 weeks before each exam, I would make a spreadsheet of some past exam questions that would be good practice. Example. </li> <li> We would each “sign-up” to be responsible for certain past exams, solve the exam, and upload our solution to a Google Drive. </li> <li> We would all still study everything we wanted to at our own pace (including solving past exams that were “assigned” to other people), but would meet once to briefly go over anything we wanted to emphasize from what was assigned to us. </li> <li> The benefits were two-fold. (1) As we were working and studying at our own pace, we could check our solutions against each other’s and ask questions/discuss differences. This was especially helpful when there were not any provided solutions from the professor. (2) We had a dedicated time to chat about things we were confused about or wanted to highlight as tricky/interesting. </li> <li> As the year progressed, we did not meet all too frequently, but some folks continued the practice of uploading solutions and we all were able to discuss challenging questions/compare solutions in a more fluid manner in our offices.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <u><b>Office hours:</b></u> I loved going to office hours. I was at first intimidated at first that my questions were too silly/basic, but after not doing well on my first test, it sunk in that it’s better to ask and be honest than to not. I strategically would go to our TA’s office hours when my questions were more minor/specific to a particular problem and to our professor’s office hours when I had broader questions. I also benefited from others being in office hours who had similar questions or asked questions I could ask follow-ups to. </li> <li> <u><b>What-if thinking:</b></u> By utilizing the techniques above, I began to be more excited about the concepts we were learning and tried to implement some “what-if” thinking to see how problems changed in different contexts/under different assumptions. I would ask myself (or a peer), “what if instead of ___, we had ____?” <ul> <li> Solving problems in a thematic way made me more cognizant and interested in ways in which the concepts we learned could be applied. Working in groups allowed me to bounce off other ideas to think of these questions. Reading papers also helped me discover new applications and appreciate the concepts we were learning better. </li> <li> Asking these what-if questions while studying helped me check that I understood the <i>core concepts</i> and made me more prepared in seeing each concept we learned applied in different ways. When we are tested or doing our own research, we will be solving something new and contributing to the field. “What-if” thinking helps immediately with solving problems on tests we’ve never seen before and prepares us better for doing research in later years. </li> </ul> </li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/dept-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/dept-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/dept-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/dept.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/rainbow-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/rainbow-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/rainbow-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/rainbow.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Photos of the Social Sciences and Humanities building, which houses the Economics department </div> <h2 id="prelims-preparation">Prelims Preparation</h2> <p>A lot of the second year students and other faculty instilled in us confidence that we would pass prelims. But it is easier to retrospectively say that after passing themselves! Prelims are tough! If we didn’t pass them, we’d need to retake them, and if we didn’t pass the retakes, we weren’t qualified to continue in the PhD. So the pressure was on.</p> <p>We had about 5 days between our last final exam of the quarter and the month of preliminary exams, so the entire Spring quarter was truly a grind as we were balancing prelims preparation with the coursework/exams of the quarter. I’ve never worked harder in my life - I was dreaming about solving problems in my sleep and taking very short breaks throughout the day. It was a cycle of eat, study econ, sleep, repeat.</p> <p>I began preparing for prelims over Spring break, around 10 weeks before our first prelim. My strategy encompassed:</p> <ul> <li> <u><b>Studying:</b></u> I utilized the same five techniques as described above to study. <ul> <li> Over Spring Break, I drafted a prelims plan (the “Timeline” tab here) in which I divided up, week by week, which <i>topics</i> I wanted to focus on. Then, I would get to it and solve past preliminary exam questions, past midterms/finals, and past problem set questions. Since we still had coursework for the Spring quarter, I studied for the content on Spring exams by doing past prelims on those topics. I wasn’t always able to stick to my plan, but I tried my best and prioritized where I could. </li> <li> I found the thematic plan for each subject to be very useful and it ensured that I was indeed covering my bases and not skipping reviewing any concept. Since the material on the prelims covered the entire year across all three subjects, it was very important to me that I knew exactly what could be covered and how I could practice. See the (“Micro - List”, “Macro - List”, and “Metrics - List” on this prelim planning sheet I used as an example). </li> <li> The planning also helped illustrate which models were <i>emphasized</i> more. Any time I tried to guess the topic of an exam, I was always wrong, so I did not expect that preliminary exams would be any more predictable. But it was still useful to see which models did show up more frequently. </li> </ul> </li> <li> <u><b>Mock exams:</b></u> I found it <i>extremely helpful</i> to do “mock exams” to simulate what a prelim would look like. I did 2 mock exams before each prelim. For each mock, I would choose a past prelim exam that I thought was difficult/I had not done before (so it would be the first time solving those problems for me!). Then, I would go to the exact room we would take the exam in at the exact time of our exam, and take the exam in the time limit we would get. I brought a sheet of paper with me to take some random notes on my <i>experience</i> taking each exam. <ul> <li> I took note of the following: <ul> <li> The <b>temperature</b> of the room (this would help inform how I would dress on exam day) </li> <li> Where the <b>clocks</b> were located (and if I should bring my own) </li> <li> How <b>noisy</b> the room was (Were people walking by frequently? Was the AC noisy? Would ear plugs be useful?) </li> <li> How my <b>body</b> was reacting (When did I get hungry? Should I bring more snacks than I did for the mock? How far were the bathrooms? Was I drinking enough water?) </li> <li> How to manage my <b>papers</b> (Each question was roughly 5-10 letter-sized pages for me, so I needed to figure out how to manage those pages. I learned through a mock that I should bring paper clips for each question and binder clips for the full exam). </li> <li> How much space the <b>desks</b> had (I learned from a mock that carrying a bunch of pens and pencils was overwhelming and I learned to bring a cup to keep all writing utensils in so I wouldn’t have to worry about them rolling off of my desk or taking up space) </li> <li> <b>Time management</b> (How long did I take on each question? How did I utilize the reading period?) </li> <li> <b>Chair</b> comfort (How comfortable are the chairs? Could I sit for 5 and a half hours comfortably or should I bring a cushion?) </li> </ul> </li> <li> From a content perspective, the mock exams were very valuable in forcing me to think of problems without any references. While practicing, I would always try to solve problems without resources, but I did occasionally look at my notes or the answer keys when stuck so that I could save time studying. Taking exams without references forced me to practice taking my time while solving problems and practice adding notes about my intuition if I did not feel very strongly about a result. This in turn gave me the confidence that I could solve challenging problems independently and even if I got stuck, I could write something to show what I knew. </li> <li> The mocks were extremely useful in helping me feel confident and comfortable on exam day. I was prepared with what I needed to bring, how I should manage my pages, how I should spend my time, and how my body would feel. </li> </ul> </li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>I can’t describe it, but as I was studying, beautiful moments happened where concepts “clicked” and some of the content we learned across classes started to intertwine in a way that helped me understand what we were learning more clearly. Persistence was key to finding these moments.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="prelims">Prelims</h2> <p>We had 3 preliminary exams (Macro, Micro, Metrics), which were cumulative and spaced out by one week in between each exam.</p> <ul> <li> <u><b>Day before:</b></u> The day before the prelim, I did not do any intense studying. I just reviewed my study guides and the past prelim solutions I had made. I shut off all studying by 7pm, ate a hearty dinner, and then got a good night’s rest. </li> <li> <u><b>Day of:</b></u> I got to the exam early. For some exams, our seats were assigned, and for others, we had free seating. Since I had done mock exams in the rooms, I had a pretty good idea of where I wanted to sit for the exams with free seating. So it was nice to get to the exams early. Our exams were all anonymous and the department provided the paper we were supposed to write on. Getting there early allowed me to set up my desk (and cup of pens!), lay my snacks out under my seat, and put my unique identifier on each page (so I wouldn’t have to worry about it later!). <ul> <li> During the exam itself, I tried to execute everything I learned from the mocks and stayed confident throughout. </li> <li> After the exam, I tried to not talk about it. It was done and there was nothing I could do to change what I wrote. There was no point in worrying or overthinking. </li> <li> The exams were a lot more physically demanding than the mocks (probably because of the pressure and brain power used on the test), so I took the remaining time of the day to rest and recover, and only started for the next prelim the following day. </li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>Overall, I think the prelim exams were very demanding, but I felt that the entire year was solid preparation that gave us the tools to succeed. We had an opportunity to show our professors everything we learned by solving problems we had never seen before.</p> <blockquote> <p>After going through the stress of studying for hours each day, I felt a great sense of confidence after passing them and am now really looking forward to the next year of classes.</p> </blockquote> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/6-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/6-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/6-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/6.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/5-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/5-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/5-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/5.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Pictures of our cohort </div> <h1 id="social-reflections">Social Reflections</h1> <p>Everyone is different and values socializing in different ways - to each their own! Prior to the start of the PhD program, I led a pretty social lifestyle. I wasn’t going out and partying all the time, but I definitely found a lot of joy in being an activities-oriented person: traveling, hiking, playing board games, going to museums, going to parks/on walks, going over to other people’s homes, going out to eat etc. I knew that I would not be able to stay as active since my priority was to study, learn, and pass prelims, but I wanted to find ways to do activities I enjoyed as well. While the quantity of these social activities did decrease substantially, I was able to find ways to begin building social connections at Davis, and will continue to grow those next year. Below are a few things I did to help me begin building connections with others in the community.</p> <h2 id="department-bonding">Department Bonding</h2> <p>I tried to attend every student-faculty and all-department event I could (especially if they weren’t around exam season!). For some events, there weren’t obligations to stay for the entire period of each event, so I navigated my attendance accordingly.</p> <blockquote> <p>I think networking is extremely important and sometimes undervalued in PhD programs. I strove to meet all the professors and students I could to begin laying the foundation for friendships and collaborations in the future!</p> </blockquote> <p>I also just found everyone so interesting, so I was very excited to get to know everyone better (inside and outside of academia). Meeting upper year students was also really lovely because I now have friends going into the next year and can call on them for advice.</p> <p>Below are some of the opportunities we had to bond with other students/faculty in the department:</p> <ul> <li> <u><b>Department parties:</b></u> The economics department hosted two main department-level events: a welcome party in the Fall and a spring party towards the end of the year. I really enjoyed meeting some professors and students from other years in the program. </li> <li> <u><b>Coffee-Donut-Bagel:</b></u> The Graduate Students Association representatives from the economics department would host bi-quarterly morning events in which we could have breakfast and mingle with students and faculty. Some were for students and faculty, and some were for just students. I enjoyed attending these to meet new upper year students and begin to hear about what some professors are interested in researching and doing for fun! </li> <li> <u><b>ARE-crossover events:</b></u> One of my fields of interest is development economics, so I actually was very excited about these crossover events as I knew I would interact with the ARE department in the future. We had two such events: one was a soccer tournament (the Cournot Cup) and the other was a bowling tournament. </li> <li> <u><b>Department IM sports:</b></u> I did not participate in any intramural sports, but I know that many people enjoyed playing on intramural sports teams with faculty and students across different years. Our Economics department IM Soccer team even won last year! </li> <li> <u><b>Holidays:</b></u> I tried to celebrate holidays with other people across all years. I specifically enjoyed celebrating Diwali and Lunar New Year with friends. Although I traveled during Thanksgiving, Winter break, and Spring break, I still was able to have some meals with other students at the beginning/tail-end of these breaks, and I know that people who stayed in Davis set up chats to meet up with each other. </li> <li> <u><b>Camping trips (UC Davis specific):</b></u> Every year, students in the economics department host a camping trip in Lake Tahoe. This was honestly one of the first ways I came to know some upper year students, who I later spent time with. There were other impromptu trips planned and mass-emails were sent out whenever someone had booked a campsite and had openings for others to join. </li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/cny-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/cny-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/cny-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/cny.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/diwali-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/diwali-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/diwali-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/diwali.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Diwali and Lunar New Year celebrations </div> <h2 id="cohort-bonding">Cohort Bonding</h2> <p>I absolutely loved meeting people in our cohort. People were from all over the world - Argentina, Brazil, Chile, China, Colombia, India, Japan, Paraguay, Turkey, South Korea, USA. We set up a WhatsApp group so that everyone could stay connected and organize events.</p> <p>Some notable things we did were:</p> <ul> <li> <u><b>Birthdays:</b></u> At the beginning of the year, we set up a Google Doc where everyone could note down their birthdays. We all tried to message the WhatsApp group on people’s birthdays and for those that wanted to celebrate, they’d drop an open-invitation to celebrate at a restaurant. </li> <li> <u><b>Yosemite Trip:</b></u> The majority of our cohort went on a trip to Yosemite National Park. We rented a house that could accommodate everyone and had a blast hanging out in the house and park (people split up doing different activities). </li> <li> <u><b>Studying:</b></u> We were too many people to all study in a large group, but we had an active Google Drive where people posted resources and study tools, which we shared with one another. Many people formed study groups with their officemates. </li> </ul> <h2 id="community-friends">Community Friends</h2> <p>From my experience working, I knew that for me, it was important to make friends outside of the program as well.</p> <p>The outlets that I found easy to tap into were:</p> <ul> <li> <u><b>Sports team:</b></u> I joined an Ultimate Frisbee (the sport I play!) community pick-up team that is composed of graduate students from different departments, adults, and some undergrads here and there. I found them through Google! I love playing with them and have been able to meet up with a few people outside the field! </li> <li> <u><b>Roommates:</b></u> I chose to live with non-econ-PhD, but other graduate students so that I could make more friends outside of the department. While everyone is studious and respects/understands the studying we all do, we occasionally interact via watching movies, playing board games, and having dinner together. </li> <li> <u><b>Extracurricular courses:</b></u> I know many people who took pottery classes, photography classes, yoga classes, rock-climbing courses, zumba classes etc. I did not join these classes during my first year and stuck with Ultimate Frisbee, but I am interested in trying some moving forward. </li> </ul> <h1 id="why-i-love-uc-davis">Why I love UC Davis</h1> <p>I am very happy to be studying at UC Davis. Since I am interested in migration economics, I think it is a great fit academically. Since I love the outdoors, I think it is a great fit location-wise. And since I really value team camaraderie, I think it is a great fit emotionally.</p> <p>I was pleasantly surprised by how collaborative the environment was. All of the professors I met are extremely qualified, very knowledgeable, incredibly passionate about their research, and truly thoughtful in their teaching. I constantly felt encouraged and really appreciated the enthusiasm of everyone in the department. Students from other years shared resources and advice with our cohort. And our cohort tried to build on those resources to iterate for the next year. I always felt I could message a peer if I needed help understanding a concept or problem. I always felt that the professors were interested in how we were doing both academically and emotionally. As an added bonus, I LOVE living in California – I am able to ride a bicycle to commute 30 minutes a day and live in a place extremely accessible to nature (40 minutes to Napa, 1.5 hours to Tahoe, 1.5 hours to Yosemite!).</p> <p>Despite all the all-day, every-day studying in first year (which was very stressful!), I am very happy that I was able to find small joys in everyday life.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/first_day-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/first_day-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/first_day-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/first_day.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My first day of classes, 2023 </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Part I in my series about the first year of an econ PhD where I reflect on my academic and social experience]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flourishing in the First Year - Part II. Routines</title><link href="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-routines/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flourishing in the First Year - Part II. Routines"/><published>2023-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-routines</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-routines/"><![CDATA[<p>Time can be very limiting in a rigorous PhD program. It was important for me to build certain habits for my own sanity, health, motivation levels, and happiness. I think that everyone figures out what works best for them on their own and over time - and a great place to start is during Math camp. Below are some of the most important types of routines I think are worth developing.</p> <h1 id="health">Health</h1> <p>Doing a PhD can definitely take a <i><b>physical</b></i> toll on your body. I think the majority of people in my cohort (myself included) developed some sort of back pain and strain. I even started clenching my teeth at night, which I had never done before. The intense work coupled with feelings of imposter syndrome and adjusting to a new environment also takes a <b><i>mental toll</i></b>. I personally experienced imposter syndrome and compared myself to other peers and PhD students from other departments.</p> <p>I think that everyone was quite cognizant of the ways in which these physical and mental stresses affected our bodies and everyone was surprisingly diligent in trying to proactively stay healthy. Common ways in which people prioritized health were: going to physical therapy, going to psychological therapy, walking pets, and exercising. I really appreciated that while I could see everyone working extremely hard studying all day, people did take some time each day to go on a walk, go on a run, go to the gym, talk to a therapist, etc. The nice part too is that almost everyone commuted to class by bicycle! I loved this because even if I felt I did not have time to do a specific type of work out I wanted, I still got in 30 minutes of cycling a day. I had heard that Davis was a pretty healthy environment, so I was very happy to see this in practice. Even our faculty were very supportive and active themselves - many professors also commute by bicycle, play sports, or go on hiking trips. Some professors even host “life office hours” to discuss anything about life!</p> <p>Health is something I take very seriously, and being in an environment where the type of lifestyle I lead was not only respected, but encouraged, was very nice. My health routine consisted of waking up at 6am, doing yoga before checking my phone, eating breakfast, riding a bicycle to school, eating lunch, riding my bicycle back home, eating dinner, and sleeping before 11pm to ensure I got at least 7 hours of sleep each night. I also played ultimate frisbee for two hours, twice a week. I also did a lot of meal prep and ate out very rarely, which helped me maintain a healthy diet. I am also normally really bad at drinking water, but I tried really hard to stay hydrated!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/7-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/7-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/7-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/7.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/8-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/8-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/8-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/8.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My main sources of physical activity </div> <h1 id="relationships">Relationships</h1> <p>I think that building and maintaining relationships are extremely important for inculcating a supportive environment for yourself. No one in our cohort was actually from Davis, but I noticed that everyone did put in effort to maintain connections with loved ones back home. We inevitably also built friendships with one another, either through studying with people in our offices, spending time doing cohort activities, or making plans to meet outside of campus.</p> <p>When I moved to Davis, I immediately added the timezones of people I wanted to maintain touch with on my phone and made an effort to stay in touch. Mostly, this materialized in the form of me randomly cold-calling friends and family while commuting by bike (with only one headphone in, so I could still hear my surroundings!). But I also made some plans to talk to my friends. I was lucky enough that some friends visited me and that I was also able to travel and see some friends and family during breaks. I attended all department social events as possible and tried to organize other events for our cohort as well. Staying connected with all of my family and friends really helped me feel supported during stressful periods and I appreciate all the well-wishes they sent me before exams!</p> <h1 id="development">Development</h1> <p>It is hard to build a specific routine for personal/professional development, but I tried my best to get started by participating in the following activities:</p> <ul> <li> <u><b>Seminars:</b></u> At the beginning of the quarter, I paid close attention to the invitations to join specific email lists and marked on my calendar when seminars would be held for specific fields. I set a goal for myself to attend at least one seminar per month in a field I was interested in. There were also options to meet some speakers throughout the day. I initially did not sign up for any as I did not have my own research to speak to them about. But some professors really encouraged me to meet with external speakers just to get advice and hear different perspectives on how to navigate entering the research topics I was interested in, which I did. </li> <li> <u><b>Mentorship opportunities:</b></u> At UC Davis, the Graduate Student Association matches first year students with buddies, based on interests. I really appreciated meeting with my mentor and tried to come prepared with questions and honest reflections. </li> <li> <u><b>Networking opportunities:</b></u> I tried to attend all of the department events to get to know professors in a more casual setting. Since the main outlet in which first year students connect with professors is through the first year sequence, I felt that I did not know too many of the professors whose research interests overlapped with mine. I emailed a few professors to meet with them and solicit advice about my summer plans. To my delight, all professors I emailed were more than happy to meet with me and all gave me really encouraging feedback and advice! I know that professors are all extremely busy, so I tried to enter these conversations with some specific questions regarding what advice I was seeking. </li> <li> <u><b>News:</b></u> I love listening and reading the news. It helps me feel like a more well-rounded global citizen and it inspires many research questions. Most of the news I consume is via podcasts and Twitter/X. When I am not speaking to anyone while biking or doing household chores, I am always listening to a podcast. </li> </ul> <p>Finally, I like to document the steps I make towards any personal growth. I used to maintain this habit while working and found it extremely useful in identifying patterns, figuring out what new skills I needed to build, and sharing my progress with my mentors. I also personally like having a record so that I can feel simultaneously accomplished in what I have done and motivated to do other things. <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/11ADMG0hM7a19roUm3qhdWuULX9GUy0cs2NIxXLKprJI/edit?usp=sharing">Here</a> is my current list.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/bus-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/bus-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/bus-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/bus.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/view-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/view-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/view-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/view.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Photos from UC Davis </div> <h1 id="exam-routines">Exam Routines</h1> <p>I think everyone in our cohort developed their own exam routine based on the study habits that worked for them. As I reflected on in the <a href="https://mitali-mathur.github.io/blog/2023/first-year-reflections/">previous post</a>, I began studying for exams 2 weeks before each test. I found it most helpful to begin studying for exams by making a plan/mapping out all the practice problems I wanted to complete, creating study guides to summarize main concepts, and working with a study group. I liked starting to prepare early for exams because building the study guides and skimming through the problems I intended on practicing normally inspired many questions that I could ask my peers, TAs, and professors without feeling like I was learning something last minute, since I knew that it took me longer for concepts to sync in. Some people preferred to study in a more concentrated manner closer to the exam date than spread out like I did, but I think it worked for them!</p> <p>During this 2 week period of studying, I was also extra cognizant of being on my phone. What an easy way to waste time! I would reduce my time-allowance on social media to 10 minutes a day and try to ensure that my screen time was low.</p> <p>On the day of any exam, I had a very specific (and maybe superstitious) routine. I would wake up, make a bigger breakfast than normal (with eggs!) and go to school at my usual time (7:45am). I would review my study guides and review the problems I had practiced. I would stop studying within an hour of the exam and try to go for a walk before or get some sunlight if the weather was nice. I get really nervous cramming or seeing others study right before, so I tried my best to step out of the office. I think the key is just to find out what works for you and follow it through!</p> <h1 id="budgeting">Budgeting</h1> <p>Being a full time student means not working full time. As such, I found it extremely important to budget. I know this is very old school, but in college, I had built myself an expense tracker and budgeting tool on excel, which I continued to use while working and in the PhD program. I know other people who use apps to track expenses as well. I was very diligent in checking that my fellowship and teaching assistant payments were going through and marking all expenses. I think this was key to ensuring I could budget for all of the trips and activities that I had planned.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Part II in my series about the first year of an econ PhD where I reflect on habits I built]]></summary></entry></feed>